[SPEAKER_01]: Discerning a mind of ill-will or lust is beneficial for not acting out of those intentions.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why is it beneficial to discern a neutral mind?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, because the neutral... neutral mind, how you call it, or neutral feeling... because if that's not discerned,
[SPEAKER_00]: A person is kind of automatically abiding in a certain, say, activated state.
[SPEAKER_00]: Let's say that way.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you're not discerning a neutrality of your mind, you're looking past it, and that looking past always implies some involvement, some pressure, some direction, which means you're gonna land on either lust or aversion, depending which way it takes you, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, one needs to be withdrawn from lust, withdrawn from aversion, but neutrality needs to be discerned, because it's not recognized as peaceful.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not recognized as the right balance.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why discerning the neutral feeling is what will establish the mind in samādhi.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even more so than through being imperturbable in regard to lust and aversion, which is also, as I said, a necessary step.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the neutrality in and of itself, when seen, when understood, it's pleasant and peaceful and recognized as such.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which means then, the mind will have even less of an incentive to turn back to desire or ill-will or other forms of engagement with the world and activations and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I can discern that there is a neutral feeling and practically, what
[SPEAKER_01]: What extra steps do I need to take to become more established?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, yeah, you should, like... Yeah, everybody would have, say, some recognition of neutral feeling, neither pleasant nor unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's neither good nor bad.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, as I said, the tendency of a mind that's still not trained, not free from craving completely, is to... well, to have some resistance towards that neutrality.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, like, whenever a person, whenever you find yourself in a situation that's, you know, neither disturbing, not really unpleasant, not terribly pleasant either, kind of just even, you need to actively make the effort to discern, to contemplate the peacefulness of it, the value of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because the mind will not see it magically on its own.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not going to be like a grand reveal of, look at this peace.
[SPEAKER_00]: You got to work through that, as I said, subtle kind of resistance that the mind has towards neutrality, and actually teach it, no, no, no, this is peaceful.
[SPEAKER_00]: This is the balance.
[SPEAKER_00]: Protect this.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it's not going to be obvious in and of itself.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, as I said, peace, it's often for people, becomes boredom.
[SPEAKER_00]: It becomes something you just... right, okay, fine, but what's next?
[SPEAKER_00]: What's the next involvement?
[SPEAKER_00]: What's the next activation?
[SPEAKER_00]: Where's the next engagement?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because that's what keeps the mind... well, kind of content in a way.
[SPEAKER_00]: People are contented by being engaged and driven, because otherwise...
[SPEAKER_00]: Feeling neutral, feeling bored, it becomes... it becomes, like, too heavy.
[SPEAKER_00]: It becomes something, like, you don't want to feel, because, again, there's no recognition of the value of that.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, contemplate the peaceful aspect of the neutral feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: And when you notice the mind, kind of, resisting, wanting to move on to the next thing, it's like, well, no, why?
[SPEAKER_00]: Hold on.
[SPEAKER_00]: What's the rush?
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, I spent my whole life moving from one thing to the other.
[SPEAKER_00]: I can spend another hour not moving on to the next thing and just stay with this neutral feeling, even if the mind starts to resist it and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, would that increase the contrast between the neutral feeling and pleasant feeling and painful feeling?
[SPEAKER_00]: Not sure if I would put it that way.
[SPEAKER_00]: I think it would more like increase mind's familiarity.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, because the more you overlook the feeling, the more driven you are by it, naturally.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, just a very ignorant, uninstructed person, that has no concept of recollecting, you know, what's currently felt, or practicing restraint, or saying no to the initial impulse.
[SPEAKER_00]: The reason why they're so driven is because they are perpetually looking way past what's being felt as the immediate
[SPEAKER_00]: Direct kind of pressure, which is the reason for motivation and for the action, and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the more you're becoming familiar with it, the more space is created between you and that impulse to act out, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_00]: In other words, it will be less and less urgent for you to, yeah, I must address this feeling, I must get rid of the unpleasure, this pleasure, I must pursue the pleasure, I, you know, I can't help but acting out of like...
[SPEAKER_00]: It will take longer for that momentum of craving
[SPEAKER_00]: To get to its force, to its full force, which means you have more time to say no to it and subdue it and not act out of it.